foreign
[Music]
Canal on its journey to Singapore
you know what is this yeah I think it's
some sweets safety suits or something
yeah it's a bulletproof
in the spring of 2009 its sister ship
was hijacked off the Somalia Coast
an event which still haunts the crew on
the bow Cecil
we thank you
oh
um
foreign
has been at sea for more than 30 years
but this kind of equipment is a first
even to this veteran
the sea route through the Suez Canal and
the Gulf of Aden is one of the major
transport highways of the Seas
each month more than 2 000 vessels use
this important trading route between
Asia and Europe
it is in these Waters that the Somali
pirates are wreaking havoc
the captain of the bow Cecil summons his
crew to a general meeting to inform and
advise about their dangerous Journey
welcome to this general meeting
we get attacked
we will sound the alarm
and if
the parents are coming
I don't think it will
help anybody to try our Sylvester
Stallone or something like that
20 year old Nancy is the only woman
among the 27 crew members
[Music]
at the same time the Norwegian warship
fridge of nansen has also arrived in the
Red Sea on its way to join the recently
established EU task force to combat
piracy operation at Atlanta
foreign
Dutchman Peter bent has the overall
command of the 12 warships assigned to
patrol and protect a sea area larger
than the entire United States
if Somalia slides will further also buy
piracy that is a security risk for the
whole world
80 percent of of trade of goods and
energy
is is transported overseas so it is it
is vital for everyone that we've that we
fight as friend
[Music]
the future of nonsen is among the newest
and most sophisticated ships in the task
force
[Music]
for this occasion it's been equipped
with prison Barracks robotic machine
guns and super fast speedboats operated
by no ways Navy Seals
foreign
[Music]
started
twenty-year-old Ina has been in the Navy
for almost a year
that is
today she and the rest of the crew will
have their first taste of the realities
of pirate hunting
foreign
[Music]
again
foreign
[Music]
the city of Odessa Ukraine
[Applause]
from this Black Sea port cargo vessel
Faida set out to sea in September 2008
on its way to Kenya and Sudan
foreign
[Music]
for the first time Sergey and his
friends talk about their ordeal after
they were hijacked by pirates in the
Gulf of Aden an event which triggered
the Western Naval offensive against the
Pirates
on September 25th 2008 the Faina enters
the Gulf of Eden carrying an ominous
cargo
foreign
Christian
reports
[Music]
instructions
foreign
[Music]
on board the tanker bowel Cecil the crew
has started their final preparations
before crossing the dangerous Gulf of
Aden
oh
[Music]
foreign
in addition to the barbed wire and the
floating ropes the captain has decided
to extend hoses with boiling hot steam
along the sides
the ship will be turned into a floating
Fortress
foreign
[Applause]
Manila
Commerce
have you wanna press
[Music]
your fingers
Ali Arif is only 29 years old and
already the commander of a group of 20
Pirates
piracy has made him a rich man here in
ale city that has been called the pirate
capital of Somalia
off the beach lies Ali's latest Bounty a
Filipino ship that he soon hopes will
bring Ransom
support
the Philippines
[Music]
the sea outside of ale used to be filled
with tuna fish lobster and shrimp
then the foreign has arrived with modern
fishing ships trawling the reefs bear of
life
with their livelihood gone the
population here had no other choice but
to turn to piracy according to Somali
human rights Advocate Mohammed Waldo
it's merely a desperate response of a
desperate people
of death spread fishermen of desperate
Community it's a desperate response
[Music]
foreign
the warship fridge of nonsen has been
assigned to escort the bow Cecil for a
few miles
[Laughter]
so
thank you
it's a bit of nonsense
foreign
the Ukrainian cargo vessel Faina barely
managed to send a Mayday signal before
the Pirates were on board
in just minutes the 17 frightened
Sailors were captured and forced into a
tiny cabin of just 12 square meters
foreign
managed to hide his mobile phone
telephone
number
these are his own video images of their
captivity
which was to last for four full months
the Faina is taken to the pirate Port of
habio
meanwhile an American warship arrives to
monitor the situation
[Music]
as the weeks go by the crew realizes
that their shipping company in Odessa is
not going to pay the ransom anytime soon
in the tiny cabin
people are starting to get on each
other's nerves
foreign
the weather is gradually improving
making the conditions ideal for small
Pirates gifts
[Music]
a surveillance plane has spotted a
suspicious boat
the nonsense gets the assignment
foreign
despite the amount of guns and pirate
equipment found EU procedures do not
permit the crew of the nansen to
interrogate the suspects
there is no law against carrying guns in
international waters and the evidence
might not secure a conviction in Kenya
the country designated to prosecute the
suspects in a court of law
hesitatingly the Norwegian Commander
finally decides to let the Pirates go
voice foreign
the Pirates get a serving of sandwiches
water and Halal chicken
foreign
but then something happens
the Pirates apparently don't want to
leave
no Waypoint no weapons
and don't know the direction
so
one six one
degree
[Music]
meanwhile onboard the bow Cecil the news
of the military's latest pirate
encounter has struck like a bombshell
yeah
foreign
[Music]
um
conditioner
foreign
[Music]
a few pirates still end up in the
custody of the western navies usually in
the cases where they're caught during an
actual hijack attempt the crew on this
pirate Mothership has just been arrested
by U.S Marines
the suspects are transported to the
warship's hangar for processing
from there they're taken to Kenya to
face trial
[Music]
the Kenyans however are anything but
Overjoyed at accepting these prisoners
we only accept what we are able to to
handle in other words we bite what we
can chew
at the moment more than 100 Somali
pirates await their trials in Kenyan
jails as part of a deal that even the
country's members of parliament know
nothing about
we have raised in Parliament wanting to
know the details of this agreement which
is treated a top secret between the
United States of America and certain
nations of the European Union to provide
facilities in Kenya for the holding of
the
suspects the U.N has allocated some four
million dollars a year to help the
Kenyan justice system cope with the
large number of piracy cases
but the public defenders who will
represent the Pirates still haven't seen
any of this money
where the facilities where are the funds
I'm representing about 32 pirates of the
total of about
123 who are already here and in none of
the files have I been given even a pin
we have fairly functional
institutions
and they're being exploited by the
Western Nations who they are not
themselves take these people into their
own countries
so far on
our own full of pirates has been
convicted in Kenya
the whole Arrangement casts doubts about
the Western nation's seriousness in
wanting to combat the Somali pirates
according to writer Loretta napoleone
why taking them to Kenya I mean why not
somewhere else
this is the typical shortcut solution
governments in the west really like I
don't want to deal with its problem
therefore you know I just you know do
the minimum at huge costs for the
taxpayer
foreign
[Music]
Cecil is halfway through the Gulf of
eight when an alert lookout spots
something suspicious
because
actually I saw something
nice
foreign
[Music]
Rochester I'm closing to your position
the past year has seen a tremendous
surge in piracy off the coast of Somalia
here in London the piracy has created a
whole new industry
we have a new industry of into insurance
companies security companies that ensure
and protect cargos
it's a big business as terrorism has
become a big business
if we look at you know Ransom payments
or sort of conservative estimate for
2008 around 50 million you can travel
that probably to work out the full cost
of piracy in terms of you know your
lawyers fees your extra pay to your crew
and so on increased insurance premiums
and all these additional costs filter
down to the likes of you and me I think
as consumers as shipping gets more
expensive
delegate company swinglehurst is one of
the very few Insurance Executives who
agrees to be interviewed about piracy
Insurance tailor-made for the situation
in the Gulf of Aden
you know for insurance cost things it
would be paying about maybe 10 15 000
okay to Transit
we were certainly the Pioneers in the
market and we received literally tens
dozens of inquiries so the Christmas
card list Scott suddenly you know it
went from let's say you know a tenfold
increase
some analysts believe it's problematic
that too many people now are starting to
make big money from the threat of piracy
I don't think that the word world
population is really interested in
stopping the rubber of piracy because
they do not understand
what the problem is about
here in Somalia they think the problem
is that foreigners have taken all their
fish Reserves
foreign
[Music]
try to stop this illegal fishing it's
going on in a big way now under the eyes
and nose and in fact in the protection
of the Navies
pirate Chief Ali Arif recalls the day
when he and his father met a large Fleet
of foreign trawlers at sea
um
[Music]
camera
Ali's father disappeared in the sea that
day
the choice is available to me
of being killed
by a warlord
being killed by poverty and hunger and
being killed by American Bully
I rather be American
bullet and with the chance of of winning
also something sometime
foreign
[Music]
Cecil is still being pursued by a
possible pirate boat
the warships which are here to protect
Merchant shipping have failed to answer
their distress calls
not to worship communism
thank you because
this is motor tanker power CSL
yes we have spotted a little bit
suspicious Target on our starboard side
now it is heading towards our school
foreign
[Music]
gilo
India um
[Music]
meanwhile the warship fridge of nansen
also receives a dramatic distress call
[Music]
an Italian freighter has come under
attack a few miles away Pilots have
opened fire to force it to stop
very fast
thank you now this is the European
warship I am constantly going to send
two fast-moving rips to your position
they will come fast upon your ship
foreign
[Music]
all right
because
100 days have passed since the fine I
was hijacked
for Christmas the Pirates give their
hostages a bottle of whiskey to share
among themselves and this is how they
celebrate New Year's Eve 2008.
yes
[Music]
foreign
the Pirates have demanded a ransom of 25
million dollars an amount nobody wants
to pay
London lawyer Stephen Askins is hired to
negotiate
the most difficult case that we've been
involved in was was the Faina you're
dealing with irrational people it's not
like a standard commercial negotiation
where you expect someone to start off
very high and you start off very low and
you perhaps meet in the middle there are
no real rules to it
the negotiations are at a standstill one
day the Somalians come to the cabin and
order the sailors out on Deck
is
[Music]
no
karate
America
back in the Ukraine the Pirates get the
reactions thereafter
noon
it is
due to the persistent rumors that the
Ukrainian authorities are planning a
spectacular rescue operation the mothers
of the hostages decide to start
negotiating with the Pirates themselves
is put in contact with the pirate
commander on board the Faina he calls
himself Muhammad
[Music]
is
foreign
[Music]
Cecil they still haven't heard any news
about the suspicious boat which the NATO
worship had promised to check out
home
if you have any information about this
this fishing boat we reported earlier
that
contacted like a transport though he was
carrying the gold
can you please repeat once again he was
transporting something good
yes that was a transporting gold
done more lead suspects instead
oh my God gold yeah
transporting gold
so Essentials
or something
foreign
[Music]
led by a helicopter from the Dutch
Flagship the future of nansen has set
full speed Southeast
to the men who attacked the Italian
cargo vessel
jokes
with a head start of just 10 nautical
miles the chances of finding the
culprits are good the prison Barracks
are prepared for possible guests
the crew has already received
information about the attack on the
Italian ship and the Navy's up to now
feudal hunt for the Pirates
[Music]
foreign
a Cambodia thank you speculation is
[Music]
Sailors and insurance companies no
longer believe that the military can
solve the piracy problem on their own
what we're doing what what I think the
um you know the the European you know
Naval forces are doing
um is is a short-term you know fix it's
a Band-Aid
British security company Hart is one of
the many which openly advertise their
armed services to ship owners with the
added value of huge discounts on
insurance premiums
heart provides an armed approach to
protection we are quite expensive and it
ranges from about 120 to 180 000 pounds
roughly and it depends on the type of
vessel how long because the quicker the
faster the vessel goes the less time it
needs our services on board but a
general rule of thumb is that we are
going to be about twice that of that of
a of an unarmed approach
here in the mountains of Northern Italy
the security company Sig is arranging a
selection course for future sea Marshals
uh
the chief instructor is a former
mercenary with extensive experience from
work in Africa
some of these guys that we have on this
course will go down there are willing to
go down there and we need to prepare
them for what they're going to meet
I think that it's just three four guys
on this course that is really up for it
to go out there now for a job yeah
foreign
weapons training is an important part of
the course and here is some of the
Arsenal this company offers its clients
M theater
then I call the focuses
huh
go private security contractors like
tour guy or frixen think the
international Naval forces have lost
their credibility because they're
reacting too timidly against the Pirates
his message to Future clients is this
yeah it will be worse
I definitely
there's no doubt about that
I think personally a more brutal
Collision Force that's the only thing
that could stop this
some security companies are now running
their own private fleets of armed Patrol
boats outside of Somalia there is a fear
that this trend will inevitably lead to
an escalation also from the Pirates
a pirate was telling me
you know they do have weapons that can
sink
most of the vessels
on the sea
but they have
been reluctant to do it
but if the back is brought against the
wall I don't know what they are able to
do or what they are likely to do
record
in February 2009 a Ukrainian billionaire
announced that he would pay the ransom
for the crew of the Faina
134 days after the hijacking two boxes
containing more than three million
dollars in cash are parachuted onto the
vessel's deck
is
[Music]
a few hours later the Pirates and the
money are gone
the U.S Navy moves in with much needed
food and medical supplies
[Music]
foreign
what kind of problems would it create
for your company if the piracy of
Somalia were to disappear overnight
I mean obviously it'd be sad in some
ways because you know we as I said
earlier we've probably enhanced our
earnings you know by let's say 30 35
this year
[Music]
troll many of the crew members on board
the warship fridge of nonsense have a
new impression of the Pirates they've
come to fight
um
foreign
[Music]
Cecil can finally take a break after a
30-hour nerve-wracking Passage through
the Gulf of Aden
[Music]
OS
a fence
the sailors on the merchant ship
continue their Voyage with mixed
feelings about the military and their
effort to fight the Pirates
Elizabeth
[Music]
foreign
attacks continues to increase
the cost of you know keeping this kind
of ships at Sea is astronomical so we
have to re-invent recreate a new way of
finding a piracy
we've seen how Pirates are often fed and
set free despite having clear intentions
of attacking ships because of the
underlying legal dilemmas facing the
multinational Naval forces
it's more political and publicity than
actually doing the job
it's not cost effective
it's not protective
it's not working
the overall solution is on land
what we do is see at sea is definitely
necessary but the solution is in a
stable Somalia
I think both the critics and the pirate
Hunters share is an understanding that
before the sailors of the world's
Merchant fleets can ever start to feel
safer the International Community must
do something about the conditions in
war-torn Somalia
meanwhile Pirates of Somalia are
thriving from the ever-increasing
ransoms paid by ship owners
on the beaches of pirate Capital Ale Ali
Arif is even considering raising the
stakes
[Music]
thank you
foreign
[Music]